Register of the F. Marguerite Jacobs-Pauwels papers
Hoover Institution Archives
F. Marguerite Jacobs-Pauwels papers
1899-1965
65027
Hoover Institution Archives
12 manuscript boxes (4.8 linear feet)
The F. Marguerite Jacobs-Pauwels papers provide a record of the life and career of a Belgian woman active in public service and charitable work in her native country over a period of 50 years. These activities included caring for orphaned children and wounded soldiers during and after World War I, and heading a campaign after World War II for the recognition of Belgian army veterans and resistance fighters.
Jacobs-Pauwels, F. Marguerite.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1965.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the library catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
1915-1923 Director, Foyer des Orphelins, Charleroi, Belgium
1924 Secretary, Ligue Nationale Belge contre le Péril Vénérien
1944-1952 President, L'Oeuvre des Médailles de la Libération et du Triomphe
Scope and Content of Collection
The F. Marguerite Jacobs-Pauwels papers provide a record of the life and career of a Belgian woman active in public service and charitable work in her native country over a period of 50 years. These activities included caring for orphaned children and wounded soldiers during and after World War I, and heading a campaign after World War II for the recognition of Belgian army veterans and resistance fighters.
The majority of the collection is organized into files corresponding to the various institutions and organizations Jacobs-Pauwels was associated with. The largest of these files relates to her directorship of an orphanage in Charleroi, Belgium in the years 1915-1923. The materials in this file include correspondence, administrative records, and reports concerning the operations of the institution. These documents give information on the needs of the children in the orphanage, the care that they received, as well as the various sources of funding and materials that the orphanage received. They also detail the role of the American Red Cross and the Commission for Relief in Belgium (C.R.B.) in providing aid to the orphanage.
Another important file in the papers pertains to an organization headed by Jacobs-Pauwels after World War II, l'Oeuvre des Médailles de la Libération et du Triomphe. This organization raised money to provide medals to combatants in the war, including veterans of the Belgian army and resistance movement. The file is largely comprised of correspondence and reports, with details on medal recipients and the activities of provincial committees of the organization.
Personal correspondence in the papers includes letters exchanged over many years between Jacobs-Pauwels and Charlotte Kellogg, who participated in the aid efforts of the C.R.B.. There are letters to other correspondents in which Jacobs-Pauwels expresses her views on Belgian politics. The papers also contain a small number of lectures and articles by Jacobs-Pauwels, as well as some writings by other individuals.
Arrangement Statement
The collection is arranged into 11 series: Biographical file; Correspondence; Speeches and writings; Subject file; Photographs; Hospices Civils file; Foyer des Orphelins file; Ligue Nationale Belge contre le Péril Vénérien file; L'Oeuvre des Médailles de la Libération et du Triomphe file; Speeches and writings by others; Memorabilia
Foyer des Orphelins (Charleroi, Belgium).; Orphans and orphan-asylums--Belgium--Charleroi.; World War, 1914-1918--Belgium.; World War, 1914-1918--Children.; World War, 1914-1918--Civilian relief.
- Biographical file, 1914-1965
  - Certificate, 1914 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Clippings, 1923-1924 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Curriculum vitae, 1923-1950 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Honors and distinctions, 1919-1922 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Identification cards and passes, 1914 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Letters relating to acquisition of collection, 1964-1965 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Letters relating to obtaining pension, 1922-1930 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Travel diary relating to a trip to Greece, 1946 (Box-folder 1: 8)
- Correspondence, 1914-1963
  - Unidentified, 1938-1948 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Aussems, J., 1962-1963 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Barnich, Georges, 1922-1927 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Belgian American Educational Foundation, 1946-1951 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Bourniquel, Gaston, 1937-1938 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Bourniquel, Pierre, 1937-1938 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Buisset, Suzanne, 1920-1922 (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - Camion, Amélie, 1924 (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - Cartier de Marchienne, Emile de, 1918-1944 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Chambre de Commerce Française de Bruxelles, 1932-1938 (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - Crocker, Ethel, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 1: 19)
  - Degbomont, Emile, 1946-1952
    - 1946-1949 (Box-folder 1: 20)
    - 1950-1952 (Box-folder 1: 21)
  - Derschied-Delcourt, Marie, 1919-1932 (Box-folder 1: 22)
  - Devreux, E., 1921 (Box-folder 1: 23)
    - 1945-1946 (Box-folder 1: 24)
    - 1947-1954 (Box-folder 1: 25)
  - Donard(?), Cécile, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 26)
  - Elisabeth (Queen of Belgium), 1926 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Errera, Léo, 1914-1928 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Fonteyne, André J., 1960 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Galpin, Perrin C., 1938-1957 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Gaulle, Charles de, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Haps, M., 1919-1920 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Harker, Sara, 1919-1921 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Hendricky, Hélène, 1915 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Henin, Jules, 1918-1923 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Henry, J. J. R., 1919-1924 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Hiernaux, Jules, 1934-1944 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - Hoover, Herbert, 1920-1960 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - Horion-Delchef, Madame, 1923-1944 (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - Horta, Julia, 1919-1926 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - Jacquemin, Albert, 1938 (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - Jadot, Jean, 1938 (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - Kellogg, Charlotte and Vernon, 1917-1945
    - 1917-1919 (Box-folder 2: 17)
    - 1920-1945 (Box-folder 2: 18)
  - Lambert, Henri, 1921-1922 (Box-folder 2: 19)
  - Lebon, Madame, 1915-1929 (Box-folder 2: 20)
  - Leclercq, Edmond, 1945-1958 (Box-folder 2: 21)
  - Lheureux, Ruth, 1964 (Box-folder 2: 22)
  - Longueville, Aubert de, 1933-1947 (Box-folder 2: 23)
  - Maquet, Jérôme, 1925 (Box-folder 2: 24)
  - Melchers, Richard, 1920-1921 (Box-folder 2: 25)
  - d'Otrement, Stanislas, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 2: 26)
  - Petri, Harald, 1920-1938 (Box-folder 2: 27)
  - Rasquin, Docteur, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 2: 28)
  - Robyns de Schneidauer, L., 1959 (Box-folder 2: 29)
  - Schranen, Jacqueline and W., 1926-1939 (Box-folder 2: 30)
  - Smelten, Nicolas, 1944-1947 (Box-folder 2: 31)
  - Solvay, E. John, 1958 (Box-folder 2: 32)
  - Sosson, Bernadette, 1964 (Box-folder 2: 33)
  - Sosson, Joseph, 1946-1954 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Tuck, W. Hallam, 1958 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - Union des Femmes de Wallonie, 1924-1928 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - Van der Belen, J., 1946-1960 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Vandermark, Louis, 1954 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - Vinck, Emile, 1921-1922 (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - Vinck, Valentine, 1919-1922 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - Whitlock, Nell, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 3: 8)
- Speeches and writings, 1915-1950
  - Collected lectures, 1915-1923 (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - Lecture, 1923 February 8 (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - "Les fleaux sociaux—le rôle des mères," lecture, 1924 April 4 (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - "Une nouvelle œuvre de l'enfance", 1925 (Box-folder 3: 12)
  - Miscellaneous notes, 1955-1960 (Box-folder 3: 14)
- Subject file, 1919-1959
  - Belgium, 1924-1949 (Box-folder 3: 15)
  - Buisset, Henri, 1950 (Box-folder 3: 16)
  - Commission for Relief in Belgium, 1927 (Box-folder 3: 17)
  - Devèze, Albert, 1959 (Box-folder 3: 18)
  - Falony, Edouard, 1947 (Box-folder 3: 19)
  - Glasell-Anderson, Anna, 1920 (Box-folder 3: 20)
  - Groupement National Belge, 1947 (Box-folder 3: 21)
  - Hoover, Herbert, 1921-1959 (Box-folder 3: 22)
  - Sforza, Carlo, 1947 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - World War II, 1919 (Box-folder 4: 2)
- Photographs, 1905-1950
  - 15 prints depicting Marguerite Jacobs-Pauwels, 1905-1927 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - 22 prints depiciting Marguerite Jacobs-Pauwels, 1928-1944 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - 13 prints depicting "La Clairière," residence, 1947 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - 5 prints depicting Alfred and Edmond Cohidon, and 1 print depicting Valéry Roy, 1914-1950 (Box-folder 4: 6)
- Hospices Civils file, 1899-1915
  - Accounts, 1914-1915 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Correspondence, 1914-1915
    - General, 1914 (Box-folder 4: 8)
    - Delacuvellerie, E., 1915 (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - Lists of wounded and treated soldiers, 1914 (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - Regulations, 1899 (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - Reports, 1914-1915 (Box-folder 4: 12)
- Foyer des Orphelins file, 1915-1944
  - Accounts, 1916-1921
    - Balances, 1918-1920 (Box-folder 4: 13)
    - Expenses, 1916-1921 (Box-folder 4: 14)
  - American Red Cross dossier, 1919-1923
    - Clippings, 1920-1921 (Box-folder 4: 15)
    - Correspondence, 1919-1923
      - 1919 (Box-folder 4: 16)
      - 1920 (Box-folder 4: 17)
      - 1921 (Box-folder 4: 18)
      - 1922 (Box-folder 5: 1)
      - 1923 (Box-folder 5: 2)
    - Description of Christmas celebration, 1920 (Box-folder 5: 3)
    - Organizational history and principles, 1922 (Box-folder 5: 4)
    - Playground project materials, 1921
      - Blueprints, 1921 (Box-folder 5: 5)
      - Directions for installation, 1921 (Box-folder 5: 6)
      - Instructions for games, 1921 (Box-folder 5: 7)
    - Proposal, 1920 (Box-folder 5: 8)
  - Architectural plans, 1915-1916 (Box-folder 5: 9)
  - Art works, 1919 (Box-folder 5: 10)
  - Charter, regulations, and statutes, 1916-1918 (Box-folder 5: 11)
  - Clippings, 1920-1924 (Box-folder 5: 12)
  - Correspondence, 1915-1923
    - General, 1915-1923
      - 1915 (Box-folder 5: 13-14)
      - 1916 (Box-folder 5: 15-16)
      - 1917 (Box-folder 6: 1-3)
      - 1918 (Box-folder 6: 4-5)
      - 1919 (Box-folder 6: 6)
      - 1920 (Box-folder 6: 7)
      - 1921 (Box-folder 6: 8)
      - 1922 (Box-folder 6: 9-10)
      - 1923 (Box-folder 6: 11)
    - Bouleuger, M. F., 1920-1921 (Box-folder 6: 12)
    - Bronckaert, B., 1917-1922 (Box-folder 6: 13)
    - Buisset, Emile and Suzanne, 1921 (Box-folder 6: 14)
    - Cognioul, Madame J., 1917-1918 (Box-folder 7: 1)
    - Dourlet, Achille, 1918-1920 (Box-folder 7: 2)
    - Foyer des Orphelins (Brussels), 1916-1923 (Box-folder 7: 3)
    - Foyer des Orphelins (La Louvière), 1917-1919 (Box-folder 7: 4)
    - Keiffer, H., 1920 (Box-folder 7: 5)
    - Pater, Arthur, 1916-1919
      - 1916-1917 (Box-folder 7: 6)
      - 1918-1919 (Box-folder 7: 7)
  - Deposition, 1918 (Box-folder 7: 8)
  - Documents relating to the tenure of F. Marguerite Jacobs-Pauwels as orphanage director, 1915-1934
    - Arrival, 1915 (Box-folder 7: 9)
    - Departure, 1922-1934 (Box-folder 7: 10-12)
  - Inventory, 1922 (Box-folder 7: 13)
  - Lesson plans, 1916 (Box-folder 7: 14)
  - List of administrators, 1915 (Box-folder 7: 15)
  - Menus and records of food supplies, 1918 (Box-folder 7: 16)
  - Minutes of meetings, 1916-1922 (Box-folder 7: 17)
  - Notebooks, 1911-1918
    - 1911 (Box-folder 7: 18)
    - 1915 (Box-folder 7: 19)
    - 1918 (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - Notes for a history of the orphanage, 1935 (Box-folder 8: 2)
  - Personal accounts and summaries of activities by F. Marguerite Jacobs-Pauwels, 1916-1923 (Box-folder 8: 3)
  - Official notices and decrees, 1914-1922 (Box-folder 8: 4)
  - Records, 1915-1921
    - Assistance to families and individuals, 1916-1918 (Box-folder 8: 5-8)
    - Children's health, 1915-1917 (Box-folder 8: 9)
    - Donations, 1914-1922
      - General, 1914-1921 (Box-folder 8: 10-11)
      - Commission for Relief in Belgium, 1916-1919 (Box-folder 8: 12)
      - Commission for Relief in Belgium, 1918-1921 (Box-folder 9: 1)
  - Remarks, 1917 (Box-folder 9: 2)
  - Reports, 1915-1922 (Box-folder 9: 3-5)
  - Photographs, 1915-1922
    - 14 prints depicting orphans, 1915-1920 (Box-folder 9: 6)
    - 4 prints depicting orphans, 1915-1920 (Box-folder 9: 7)
    - 13 prints depicting playground dedication, 1922 (Box-folder 9: 8)
  - Post-directorship file, 1943-1952
    - Closure, 1942-1952 (Box-folder 9: 9)
    - Scandal and trial, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 9: 10)
- Ligue Nationale Belge contre le Péril Vénérien file, 1924
  - Correspondence and invitation, 1824 (Box-folder 9: 11)
  - Reports and speech, 1924 (Box-folder 9: 12)
- L'Oeuvre des Médailles de la Libération et du Triomphe file, 1934-1961
  - Address list, 1948 (Box-folder 10: 1)
  - Announcements, appeals, and bulletins, 1944-1947 (Box-folder 10: 2)
  - Clippings, 1944-1952 (Box-folder 10: 3)
  - Cap Ferrat dossier, 1948-1960
    - Clippings, 1948-1960 (Box-folder 10: 4)
    - Correspondence, 1945-1950 (Box-folder 10: 5)
    - Reports, 1948-1951 (Box-folder 10: 6)
  - Correspondence, 1944-1961
    - General, 1944-1961
      - 1944 (Box-folder 10: 7)
      - 1945 (Box-folder 10: 8-9)
      - 1946 (Box-folder 10: 10-11)
      - 1947 (Box-folder 10: 12)
      - 1948 (Box-folder 10: 13)
      - 1949 (Box-folder 10: 14)
      - 1950-1959 (Box-folder 11: 1)
      - 1960-1961 (Box-folder 11: 2)
    - Belgian government, 1945-1946 (Box-folder 11: 3)
    - Medal recipients, 1945-1948 (Box-folder 11: 4-5)
    - Provincial committees, 1945-1949
      - Alost, 1945 (Box-folder 11: 6)
      - Antwerp, 1945-1947 (Box-folder 11: 7)
      - Brussels, 1945-1946 (Box-folder 11: 8)
      - Gand, 1945-1946 (Box-folder 11: 9)
      - Hainaut, 1945 (Box-folder 11: 10)
      - Liège, 1945-1949 (Box-folder 11: 11)
      - Mons, 1946 (Box-folder 11: 12)
      - Namur and Luxembourg, 1946 (Box-folder 11: 13)
      - Renaix, 1946 (Box-folder 11: 14)
      - Verviers, 1945-1946 (Box-folder 11: 15)
    - Relating to Gaston J. Sermant, 1945-1952 (Box-folder 11: 16)
    - Bagage, Jules, 1945-1952 (Box-folder 12: 1)
    - Brown, Milton, 1945-1949 (Box-folder 12: 2)
    - Delbrouck, Jean, 1946-1949 (Box-folder 12: 3)
    - Didion, Honoré, 1945 (Box-folder 12: 4)
    - Gatz, Emile, 1946-1947 (Box-folder 12: 5)
    - Joset, Camille, 1947-1951 (Box-folder 12: 6)
    - Pirard, Alfred, 1946-1947 (Box-folder 12: 7)
    - Simon, Jules, 1947 (Box-folder 12: 8)
    - United States Army, 1945 (Box-folder 12: 9)
    - Van Acker, Achille, 1947 (Box-folder 12: 10)
  - Interview, 1944 (Box-folder 12: 11)
  - List of patrons, 1945 (Box-folder 12: 12)
  - Notes, 1946-1947 (Box-folder 12: 13)
  - Pamphlets, 1948 (Box-folder 12: 14)
  - Photographs, 1934-1944
    - Two prints depicting a Belgian stamp, 1934 (Box-folder 12: 15)
    - 11 prints depicting medals and plaques, 1944 (Box-folder 12: 16)
  - Publicity materials, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 12: 17)
  - Reports, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 12: 18)
  - Statutes, 1944 (Box-folder 12: 19)
  - Miscellany, 1945 (Box-folder 12: 20)
- Speeches and writings by others, 1910-1936
  - Kopp, René, 1929-1936 (Box-folder 12: 21-24)
  - Pater, Arthur, 1910 (Box-folder 12: 25)
- Memorabilia, 1914 (Box-folder 12: 26)